Guide to the Associated Students of the University of Montana Records 1906-2012
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Associated Students of the University of Montana records
1906-2012
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 063
University of Montana. Associated Students of The University of Montana
22.1 linear feet
Meeting minutes, correspondence, financial records, scrapbooks and other materials generated by the Associated Students of The University of Montana (ASUM), the student government for The University of Montana-Missoula campuses.
Historical Note
The Associated Students of The University of Montana (ASUM) is the university's student government organization. Founded in May of 1906, ASUM serves as a forum for students to express their needs to The University of Montana administration as well as to the Montana state government. From 1936-1965, the organization was known as the Associated Students of Montana State University (ASMSU) reflecting the name change of the university. In its early years ASUM operated a general store and the university bookstore; today one of its primary functions is the allocation of money to student groups through yearly student group requests and a once a year budgeting process.
This record group contains correspondence, budget records, general store records, scrapbooks, miscellaneous materials, general ASUM meeting minutes, Central Board Meeting Minutes and other records generated from 1906-2010.
This collection has been divided into six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 0.2 linear ft., 1941-1989
Series II: Miscellaneous Records, 2.9 linear ft., 1958-2010
Series III: Budget records, 1.4 linear ft., 1933-1980
Series IV: General Store records, 0.2 linear ft., 1920-1922
Series V: Meeting Minutes, 9 linear ft., 1906-2012
Series VI: Scrapbooks, 8 linear ft., 1977-2010
Series VII: Organizational and legal, 0.2 linear ft., 1969-2007
Series VIII: Associated Students Store, 0.2 linear feet, 1959-1988
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The majority of records were held by ASUM until their transfer to the Archives. The contents of series VIII, Student Store Records, were donated to the Archives in 2020 with the Morris McCollum papers (Mss 959) and placed in this collection.
The records in this collection were transferred to the Archives on multiple dates, most recently in 2008, 2011, 2012, 2014 and 2020.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana State University (Missoula). Associated Students--Archives; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.). Associated Students--Archives; University of Montana--Missoula. Associated Students--Archives; University of Montana--Missoula--Students--Societies, etc; Montana State University (Missoula). Associated Students; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.). Associated Students
College stores--Montana--Missoula; College student government--Montana--Missoula
Missoula; Colleges and Universities
- Correspondence, 1941-1989; Series I; 0.2 linear ft.
  - Correspondence, 1941-1954 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Misc. Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 28/8)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1958-2010; Series II; 2.9 linear ft
  - Athletic Budget, 1958-1972 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - "History of ASUM," by Jeff Gray, ASUM Vice President, 1979 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Library Ad Hoc Committee, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Student Union Study, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Remarks of Loren Haar, ASUM President, 1967 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - ASUM Study Report, 1989 (Box-folder 28/6)
  - Board of Regents, 1995-2008 (Box-folder 28/7)
  - Activity Fee, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 29/5)
  - Accreditation Sub Committee Three, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 29/6)
  - Griz LAX (Lacrosse), 2008-2009 (Box-folder 29/7)
  - Lobbyist Information, 2009 (Box-folder 29/8)
  - ASUM members retirement in UM system, 1986 (Box-folder 29/9)
  - Safety on Campus, 2004 (Box-folder 29/10)
  - Campus Safety Committee, 2008 (Box-folder 29/11)
  - Sustainability, 2007 (Box-folder 29/12)
  - Third floor renovation, 1998 (Box-folder 29/13)
  - Transportation, 2006-2008 (Box-folder 29/14)
  - Information Technology, 2002 (Box-folder 30/1)
  - Leadership Development Manual, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 30/2)
  - Mansfield Center, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 30/3)
  - RFP for Beverage contract, 2009 (Box-folder 30/4)
  - Risk Management, 1995 (Box-folder 30/5)
  - Fall Retreat, 1984-2009 (Box-folder 30/6)
  - Fall Retreat, 2010 (Box-folder 30/7)
  - Clippings, 1981-2005 (Box-folder 30/8)
  - Aber Day Proclamation, 1983 (Box-folder 30/9)
  - Word Processing Recommendation Report, 1983 (Box-folder 30/10)
  - Associated Students Store, 1976-1988 (Box-folder 30/11)
  - ASUM miscellaneous committees and planning, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 30/12)
  - ASUM Senate Emergency Session, 1988 (Box-folder 30/13)
  - ASUM Presidential Briefing booklet, 1991 (Box-folder 30/14)
  - Allocation of ASUM space at University Center, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 30/15)
  - Student Affairs Group Meeting, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 30/16)
  - ASUM and other student parking in the University District, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 31/1)
  - ASUM Committees, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 31/2)
  - PEW Roundtable, 1995 (Box-folder 31/3)
  - Student Group Affairs meeting, 1994 (Box-folder 31/4)
  - Campus recreation, 1975-1996 (Box-folder 31/5)
  - Dining Services, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 31/6)
  - ASUM resignations, 1992 and undates (Box-folder 31/7)
  - Five Rivers Festival of the Fim, 1998 (Box-folder 31/ 8)
  - Student Satisfaction Summary, 1998 (Box-folder 31/9)
  - KBGA employment problems, 2000 (Box-folder 31/10)
  - Students, Standard 3 Report, 2003 (Box-folder 31/11)
  - Alcoholic beverages on campus, 1982-1999 (Box-folder 31/12)
  - Water permit, 1982 (Box-folder 31/13)
  - Physical plant, 1986 (Box-folder 31/14)
  - ASWMC Elections, undated (Box-folder 31/15)
  - Central Board officers, 1981 (Box-folder 31/16)
  - Student Participation in Mandatory Fee Decision, 1987 (Box-folder 31/17)
  - College and University Funding, 1982 and 1988 (Box-folder 31/18)
  - Disability miscellaneous, 1984-1985 and miscellanous (Box-folder 32/1)
  - Disability lawsuit, 1991 (Box-folder 32/2)
  - Disability Services, 1997 (Box-folder 32/3)
  - ASUM congressional lobbying, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 32/4)
  - Weed management, 1996 (Box-folder 32/5)
  - Kyi-Yo Indian Club, 1996 (Box-folder 32/6)
  - Student Affairs Advisory Council, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 32/7)
  - Miscellaneous funding, 1979-1999 (Box-folder 32/8)
  - ASUM Vice President Impeachment, 1994 (Box-folder 32/9)
  - Phoenix, 1988 and 1997 (Box-folder 32/10)
  - University Center, 1980-1993 (Box-folder 32/11)
  - University Theater, 1999 (Box-folder 32/12)
  - Budget planning, 2000-2003 (Box-folder 32/13)
  - UM Strategic Direction, 2003 (Box-folder 32/14)
  - MAS annual dues, 2005 (Box-folder 32/15)
  - U of M South Campus Residential Development, 2005 (Box-folder 32/16)
  - University Center, 1994-2007 (Box-folder 32/17)
  - ASUM lobbying, 2005 (Box-folder 32/18)
  - Summary of ASUM/BOR Issues, 2005 (Box-folder 32/19)
  - Academic Achievement, 2010 (Box-folder 32/20)
  - CRB meeting recorded on audio tape, 1996 (Box-folder 32/21)
  - ASUM Information for Students, undated (Box-folder 32/22)
  - Recognized ASUM Student Groups, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 32/23)
  - ASUM Election Results, 1998-2008 (Box-folder 32/24)
  - Memory Book, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 32/25)
- Budget Records, 1933-1980; Series III; 1.4 linear ft.
  - Budget Records, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Budgets binder, 1933-circa 1977 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Budget and Finance Committee binder, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - ASUM Budgets History binder, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Budget and Request, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Budget and Request, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Budget, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Budget, 1974 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Budget and Requests, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Budget and Requests, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Budget and Requests, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Budget and Requests, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Budget and Requests, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Budget and Requests, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Budget and Requests, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Budget and Requests, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Budget and Requests, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Budget and Requests, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Budget and Requests, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Budget and Requests, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Budget and Requests, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Budget and Requests, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Miscellaneous financial and budget, 1994-2006 (Box-folder 29/1)
  - Miscellaneous budget, 2009 (Box-folder 29/2)
  - General and Financial History of ASUM, 1906-1988 (Box-folder 29/3)
  - Division of Student Affairs, Budget Planning Documents, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 29/4)
- General Store records, 1920-1922; Series IV; 0.2 linear ft.
  - Order record and purchase register, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - General Ledger, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - General Ledger, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - General and Purchase Ledger, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 2/16)
- Meeting Minutes, 1906-2012; Series V; 9.0 linear feet
  The following ASUM minutes are not in this collection: June 4-December 31, 1958; 1973; 1979-1981. This series also includes scattered copies of Montana Associated Students (MAS) minutes, 1983-1988 and Central Board minutes, agendas, roll calls, and votes, 1979-1983.
  - June 1906-January 1918 (Box-volume 13/1)
  - May 1921-May 1928 (Box-volume 13/2)
  - December 1928-April 1933 (Box-volume 13/3)
  - 1919-October 1921, April 1933-May 1934 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - February 1919-May 1944 (Box 3)
  - October 1944-June 1957 (Box 4)
  - October 1957-May 1965 (Box 5)
  - May 1965-December 1971 (Box 6)
  - January 1972-August 1976 (Box 7)
  - September 1976-December 1978 (Box 8)
  - October 1982-October 1983 (Box 15/2)
  - October 1983-May 1984 (Box 15/3)
  - January 1984-June 1986 (Box 9)
  - October 1986-November 1989 (Box 10)
  - January 1990-May 1992 (Box 11)
  - September 1992-May 1997 (Box 12)
  - September-December, 1997 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - January-April 22, 1998 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - April-December, 1998 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - February-April, 1999 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - April-December, 1999 (Box-folder 14/5)
  - January-May, 2000 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - September-December, 2000 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - January-April, 2001 (Box-folder 14/8)
  - May-December, 2001 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - January-April, 2002 (Box-folder 14/10)
  - May-December, 2002 (Box-folder 14/11)
  - January-April, 2003 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - May 2003-May 2004 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - May 2004-May 2005 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - September 2005-May 2006 (Box-folder 25/1)
  - August 2006-May 2007 (Box-folder 25/2)
  - August 2007-April 2008 (Box-folder 25/3)
  - August 2008-December 2008 (Box-folder 25/4)
  - January 2009-May 2009 (Box-folder 25/5)
  - September 2009-December 2009 (Box-folder 25/6)
  - January 2010-May 2010 (Box-folder 33/1)
  - September 2010-December 2010 (Box-folder 33/2)
  - January 2011-May 2011 (Box-folder 33/3)
  - August 2011-October 2011 (Box-folder 33/4)
  - November 2011-December 2011 (Box-folder 33/5)
  - January 2012-March 2012 (Box-folder 33/6)
  - April 2012-May 2012 (Box-folder 34/1)
  - Central Board Minutes, Winter 1979 (Box 26/1)
  - Central Board Minutes, Spring 1979 (Box 26/2)
  - Central Board Minutes, Fall 1979 (Box 26/3)
  - Central Board Minutes, Winter 1980 (Box 26/4)
  - Central Board Minutes, Spring 1980 (Box 26/5)
  - Central Board Minutes, Fall 1980 (Box 26/6)
  - Central Board Minutes, Winter 1981 (Box 26/7)
  - Central Board Minutes, Spring 1981 (Box 26/8)
  - Central Board Minutes, Fall 1981 (Box 27/1)
  - Central Board Minutes, Winter 1982 (Box 27/2)
  - Central Board Minutes, Spring 1982 (Box 27/3)
  - Central Board Minutes, Fall 1982 (Box 27/4)
  - Central Board Minutes, Winter 1983 (Box 27/5)
  - Central Board Minutes, Spring 1983 (Box 27/6)
  - Central Board Minutes, Fall 1983 (Box 27/7)
  - Montana Associated Students (MAS) minutes, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 34/2)
  - Montana Associated Students (MAS), 2006-2009 (Box-folder 34/3)
- Scrapbooks, 1977-2010; Series VI; 8.0 linear ft.
  The scrapbooks mostly contain articles from the student newspaper, the Montana Kaimin, and occasional articles from the Missoulian, photos, and memos.
  - 1977-1979 (Box OS 16)
  - 1980 (Box OS 16)
  - 1981-1982 (Box OS 16)
  - 1982-1983 (Box OS 17)
  - 1984-1985 (Box OS 17)
  - 1985-1986 (Box OS 18)
  - 1986-1989 (Box OS 19)
  - 1989-1990 (Box OS 20)
  - 1991-1992 (Box OS 20)
  - January-April 1995 (Box OS 21)
  - September 1995-April 1996 (Box OS 21)
  - September 1996-September 1998 (Box OS 21)
  - October 1998-April 2000 (Box OS 22)
  - September 2000-May 2001 (Box OS 22)
  - September 2001-May 2002 (Box OS 22)
  - July 2002-April 2003 (Box OS 23)
  - August 2002-May 2003 (Box OS 23)
  - August 2005-April 2006 (Box OS 24)
  - August 2006-April 2007 (Box OS 24)
  - April 1990-December 1994 (Box OS 35)
  - September 2003-April 2005 (Box OS 35)
  - August 2007-May 2009 (Box OS 36)
  - September 2009-May 2010 (Box OS 36)
- Organization and legal records, 1969-2007; Series VII; 0.2 linear ft
  - ASUM Bylaws, 1969-1980 (Box-folder 28/1)
  - ASUM Bylaws, 1980-2005 (Box-folder 28/2)
  - ASUM Resolutions, 1974-1990 (Box-folder 28/3)
  - ASUM Resolutions, 1992-2003 (Box-folder 28/4)
  - ASUM legal, 2004-2007 (Box-folder 28/5)
  - ASUM Constitution, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 28/9)
- Associated Student’s Store, 1959-1988; Series VIII; 0.2 linear ft
  The Associated Student’s Store was started in 1922 by two students. The first store was a table by the psychology building (then the Law Building). The original stock consisted of pens, pencils, and candy. The store then grew and moved into the “Shack” behind Main Hall, where the continued to sell supplies, candy, and a small concessions area with sandwiches. With the student population continuing to grow, the Associated Student’s store soon outgrew their space and moved into the basement of the present day Fine Arts building in 1937. The store was disincorporated from the university in the early 1950s, but reincorporated when University of Montana President McFarland left office. The store moved into the second floor of the Lodge (now the Emma Lommasson Center) in 1954, then into the new base of operations in the University Center when the building was constructed in 1969.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Student Store Committee Meeting Minutes, 1959-1972 (Box-folder 37/1)
  - Student Store Committee Meeting Minutes, 1972-1988 (Box-folder 37/2)
  - Associated Student’s Store Cash Sale Receipt Book, undated (Box-folder 37/3)